this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio net.
SC radio is brought to you by the I Triple E Computer Society.
I Triple E software magazine online at computer org slash software.
for software engineering radio, this is Robert bloomin.
I have with me today bount Rooker Berendt.
has been involved in software development for over 15 years.
with a focus on automating core workflows for enterprises including t-mobile and Lufthansa.
he's contributed to open source workflow engines.
and is the author of a book on business process modeling.
which is now in its fifth edition and is available in English German and Spanish.
he regularly speaks at conferences and has many slide decks and articles on workflow management.
on SlideShare and on the Internet.
Ferrand welcome to software engineering radio.
hi I'm really pleased to have you today.
because we're gonna be talking about orchestrating micro services with workflow.
it's a topic of great interest to me.
and I'm really pleased to see that you've done so much in that area.
as I said we will be talking about orchestrating micro services with workflow.
I want to start out with the building blocks of that topic.
please give us a brief overview of micro services.
listeners can also go back and listen to show 2:13 on micro services for more about that topic.
so from my perspective there are the most important thing about micro services is basically.
that you slice down functionality or or capabilities of the software into smaller pieces.
and that I mean technology right that can result in like different things.
nowadays it might be micro services or if you go server list it might be functions.
or it might be bigger but the core thing is that you slice it down into relatively autonomous and isolated parts.
and if you do this then you start getting a lot of like new challenges.
you probably solve a lot of challenges because you know can scale up your development.
the single services get easier to do but you you get a lot of new challenges.
and the micro servers have to collaborate to communicate with each other.
to solve let's say like the bigger problems your company might want to solve towards your customer.
we will be talking a lot about how my services work together.
I want to go into another building block for this discussion, business process.
what is a business process?
you probably also want to call it a business capability.
so normally your your company offers some kind of service towards the customer.
these are the most prominent business capabilities you normally have.
I have a lot of order fulfillment examples.
because you know people relatively know order fulfillment from a customer perspective.
so you could say the order fulfillment that's one business process.
from you click on submit the order until you really have the parcel in your hands at your doorbell basically.
and we have a lot of these like business processes and companies going on.
also like smaller ones you're probably within the order fulfillment.
you might want to do payment, payment might be a known business process going on.
and yeah that's what's basically about.
so normally these kind of business processes also involve like multiple micro services in order to get going.
and that's quite an interesting area to explore.
I have a list from one of your articles of typical examples of business processes. that are amenable to workflow.
order fulfillment, invoice management, billing approval of things, stock trading, content preparation.
these are the core activities that an organization does in order to fulfill its mission and make money. that correct?
that's that's more or less correct.
we probably go into a virtual automation like as a like like a technology workflow engines.
and so on so forth later on a bit.
so I think there are two kinds of let's say workflow.
so one are these can't like core business processes what you just mentioned.
but I also see a lot of much more technical more fine-grained smaller workflows going on in companies.
just for for making relatively small things.
so as an example we really dive very deep in technology.
we have now architectures for example using messaging like RabbitMQ for example.
and then if you if you consume a message want to do some business logic send a response message.
and probably send like fan-out another additional messages like events.
then this is also already a small workflow we tackle with refrigerants nowadays as well.
so that's a quite quite huge span of use cases I see for workflow.
and these kind of like business processes I see them like the really strategic business process.
one of them you're talking about different scales.
the largest scale being the mission of the organization.
small scales being very small patterns that could occur all over the place in the fulfillment of some larger objective.
correct.
I want to come back to that scale issue.
let's do one more building block here, the idea of workflow management software.
we did show 198 on workflow management and 223 on activity.
which is an open source business process management software.
give us a brief review of what does a workflow management system do?
so the core in its core these kind of systems are basically state machines.
so they can you can run instances it's normally called of workflow.
so you create kind of a blueprint of a vert flow.
and then it can create instances and the virtual engine keeps track that you run through the blueprint.
through the model in the in the predefined order you want to have it.
and it can also persist the current state whenever you wait for something.
that's why it's a state machine basically.
and that's the core of these kind of workflow engines.
and then you have a normally like an ecosystem of tools around that.
because for example you have the modeling capabilities.
you probably want to want to have graphical models for these kind of blueprints.
you have operating capabilities like you can look into the engine what's currently going on.
is something stuck where is it stuck what's the problem what's the data attached how can I fix that?
you probably have a lot of like analyzes things in order to look into all the audit data.
these kind of engines can ride.
so what were typical paths in the in the past did they take longer?
do we have bottlenecks or room for improvements and and so on the fours.
or there's there's quite some ecosystem around and these kind of core engines.
and that's what I would define as a workflow management tool.
if I place a stock trade if it was using workflow management.
then my trade would be an instance of that workflow.
and some of the events would be the orders fulfilled a tickets generated.
exactly for example yes that's good.
okay now when we talked about workflow in these other shows.
we were not specifically talking about microservices.
we were talking about a workflow could invoke a series of steps.
and those steps would be other software that exists in the organization.
it does seem like a natural fit now the Micra service is.
that a workflow engine is using micro services to carry out the steps in the process.
is that how these two pieces fit together?
there's slight differences nowadays and I think they're really important.
so if you look back at what was called like be payments.
or like like five years back or something like that.
and this was the typical view you have like like a business process.
and that orchestrates other services in order to to get that business process implemented.
and one of the problems we got from this kind of view is that normally.
you got relatively big business processes very often tackling a lot of different domains different services.
and and probably also having different capabilities in them.
and that very often made it hard to see the right ownership in their organization.
so who really owns these kind of business process models and which team does the deployment.
which team does the running and the kind of like workflow management tools and so on and so forth.
so with micro services the perspective very much focuses on the ownership.
on the capability of one service.
so we say for example we have like the payment micro service.
and if we have the payment micro services.
the micro service that internally might require a workflow because it does stateful things.
and then I would see like the virtual engine for example.
or also the virtual model as kind of an implementation detail of that payment service.
and not anything sitting outside of it.
and and that means if you if you go further.
if you then look at the order fulfillment and micro service.
that might also have some kind of workflow included.
for example to do like the overall sequence of step like pay first and fetch the goods then ship the goods.
or so on and so forth but only these kind of issues not any details of payment.
because that's part of the payment might be service.
and that's I'm probably just slightly a different view.
but it's a different view than what we tried to do with EPM and so.
ah I hope that God somehow clear what I mean.
I have a bit of an advantage because I've been reading some of your articles to prepare for this show.
what I believe you're talking about is what I might call a federated model.
where we have order processing as the top-level objective and it would contain payment step.
and what you're saying is payment itself may then be a small work flow within a larger work flow. basically yes.
but the important detail if you look at it from a micro service perspective is that.
like order doesn't know that there is a word flow in payment it shouldn't it doesn't have to.
there's an clear API between or a clear API in front of payment.
basically that it's leveraged from the order fulfilment.
and that this is a virtual as an implementation detail in that sets.
so the top-level workflow it sees payment as service.
it doesn't know how it's implemented it's an API or a gateway.
it could be a service it goes out and does something and comes back synchronously stateless.
or it could have a small workflow embedded within it.
and that these boundaries of scale it doesn't need to know.
it's dealing with a workflow correct? correct.
okay this does seem a natural point. although I plan talked about this later.
but you've advocated architecture in which a subsystem consists of a micro service and a workflow.
to run only that micro service could you go into what you mean there and how that works.
so there I would say that it's like the view of the pure micro service paradigm.
and then you give all the micro service teams normally a higher autonomy.
and they can basically choose the tools they want to.
so you don't try to not force them into a certain tooling.
and that means in that sense they can pick the tool they want to.
and if they have a basically a problem with where they need a state machine a virtual engine.
then it's normally a natural fit that they use a virtual engine.
but they can use whatever tool they like.
I mean that's a decision they they could make on its own.
and that means like if you have different micro service different teams.
they might use also different tools some of them might use of orange and others not.
and probably even different tools.
that's like the theoretical view of a micro service perspective.
what I see in come is doing actually is that they normally try to harmonize these kind of tools.
so they they're not really eager that every team uses a different tool.
because that that's quite quite unhandy.
so then sometimes they start having like probably in one central.
but sometimes even like a couple of virtual engines.
which are reused by different services.
so that's technically that's no problem from my perspective.
then it keeps to be important that these virtual models are really owned by the different micro services.
if they then meet on the same virtual engine technically.
I mean that's doable that's that depends on what you wanna wanna achieve actually.
okay what I'm thinking of is let's take an example.
we have a micro service payment service it talks to the payment gateway and attempts to create a charge.
you have a architecture pattern where you pair that micro service up with a small workflow management.
that would handle things like retry failure card expired.
so the workflow and the service together constitute a larger entity.
which we'll call it the Augmented service.
or I don't know if you have a name for that.
so I do totally agree but I'd also don't have a name for it.
it depends a bit on I try to tune it what the customer uses for a name for this.
but basically that's the service I mean.
the service is normally made up of a couple of technical components.
so for example if you need a database that's normally also part of like logically of the service.
so and the workflow engine I also see that as part of the service.
why would I pair up this simple payment service with its own workflow manager.
and what does the augmented service do that's better than this plain payment service by itself.
it's normally all about state handling that's what I what I said.
the virtual engine is a state machine so it can persist state for however long you want to.
and that means if you have problems around state virtual engine can help you there.
and there are actually a lot of problems.
especially us already in like simple communication and distributed systems that involve state handling.
I give you a couple of examples probably.
so the first one is very easy which normally people know retrying.
so if you want to have for example you call a REST API.
you have to take care of this is not available then you probably retry.
that's something which is very often also handled in for example service masters nowaday.
which can do retry but what they do is like they do an instant retry immediately basically.
and this is very often this is not sufficient.
so there we have a lot of situations where you have to wait for a service to become available again.
in like minutes or sometimes even hours.
and in this case you probably want to have something like a stateful reach drivers.
okay I do the retry but I wait for five minutes or two hours.
or for example take insurances at least here in Europe.
a lot of them are still running on the host the host is a batch mode overnight.
so you have to wait for the host to become available to do the retry.
and these kind of things this already involves state.
another very prominent example is when you when you want to call multiple remote services like in a row.
so let's assume you call two or three rest services in in a sequence.
and the third service fails so you call it but it gives you back for example a business error.
and in this case you don't have asset transactions what we know from databases earlier on.
so we cannot simply say roll it back.
but we probably have have an error where we say oh we have to undo the other steps.
we are already called successfully.
and this is also something a virtual engine can handle that's very often called compensation.
or it's also known as the saga pattern.
it basically means that you you have to remember what you're already called.
and then you have to undo that correctly.
and that involves state because like I mean it's a distributed system.
so you might have to wait again or it takes longer.
and this is why a lot of these kind of Hubbs are stateful.
and that's basically the added value of the word for engine can give you in its core.
very often than there are additional things like visibility or operation things.
but in its core it's normally always about State.
at the beginning of the show and I don't think we quite finish this sauna comeback.
motivating why there is a need for micro services to work together with workflow.
your writing you talked about two models for this one being choreography and the other orchestration.
explain those two models.
ok so I start with choreography actually.
so they idea behind choreography is that you don't have like a central conductor that's orchestration.
but you just have different services who collaborate.
by just collaborating with each other without somebody steering that.
and that means like if we do an example again I do order fulfillment.
so if you think often for example and check-out component like a webshop for example.
that could be one micro service.
and this micro service could for example then like either doing a direct call towards like one other service.
where it says ok there was an order place.
or probably if you're event-driven it and that's actually the most famous approach the moment.
then you probably just omit an event and say ok there was an order placed.
and then some other component listens to that event that says hey there was an order place.
so I have to do something for example I have to collect the payment.
and when the payment is collected you probably omit another event that the payment was received or collected.
and then another service just starts working and that's a choreography.
because you just like having a lot of these like peer-to-peer collaborations.
either event to them or probably also like like RPC or arrested him.
and that's normally named choreography and that's got very famous recently with micro services.
there's a the famous article by Martin Fowler for example.
and he also wrote something like this is the more favorable approach for micro services.
an orchestration approach and in the contrast.
the orchestration means that there is some conductor some control.
which basically tells other services what to do.
so let's if we keep on in the order fulfillment example.
there might be it like an order fulfillment process a virtual for example.
that tells other services he retrieved the payment now and oh the payment was received.
so the next service should probably prepare the goods and so on so forth.
so there's some control in that and that's normally an named orchestration.
why are you more of an advocate of orchestration and choreography in water use cases where it is superior.
so there currently I'm advocating orchestration a lot basically.
because I see a lot of tendency towards choreography.
and there are good use cases for karaoke I can come back to that in a second.
but there are also quite a lot of risks with choreography.
which is basically that you really lose sight of what's going on in the architecture.
so if all the services are playing ping pong which with each other.
it's really hard to understand how the overall end-to-end flow through that system really works.
and there was also an article by Martin Fowler writing about that risk like beginning of last year.
so projects start to realize that and because I see that risk like for a lot of companies.
they really go down that route and and and really realize that risk.
that's why I'm advocating basically the orchestration approach a lot.
because I think people should be aware of that there is that risk with choreography.
and that it can in a lot of use cases also orchestration as a good fit.
and if you look in the essence of the two approaches.
and that's actually very interesting that it's basically the say.
the only difference is a direction kind of of coupling very off.
so if you look at the invention coupling then it's normally like a receiver decides.
that he's interested in certain events.
and if you look at orchestration normally the sender decides that he wants somebody else to do something.
so the coupling is in the center.
and for a lot of like use cases you see out there and for a lot of scenarios.
it's very natural which one is fitting better for the situation at hand.
if we take the order fulfillment it's very natural.
that there should be an order fulfillment orchestration that tells the payment to retrieve the payment.
and because that's like the ownership or of that capabilities in the order fulfillment.
and otherwise payment would have to know about orders.
and about a lot of like information about the order flow which is quite unnatural actually.
and quite hard to manage.
nothing you're saying is with choreography.
there are little bits and chunks of the order process that are distributed among each of the different services.
for example shipment has to know that it's only able to ship after payment has taken place.
with orchestration you've moved the knowledge of the business process into this one entity.
which does the orchestration which is the workflow management system is that right?
almost I would I would say I'd move that logic into the.
if I'm a micro service into the order fulfillment microservice.
and that might use leverage the workflow model for doing that.
but the core idea is that capability of orchestrating the other services.
I really moved that logic into the order fulfillment Michael service. yes.
orchestration then it's a separation of concerns.
and workflow management is a way that you can implement orchestration correct? correct.
and that's actually that's an interesting detail or an important detail I think.
because you can implement orchestration without the workflow engine.
so if you can do that hard-coded the order fulfillment if you like.
and that's already auth orchestration.
so it's not about any any kind of let's say workflow engines.
where even a lot of people think about some centralized huge engines which is not true.
I mean it's it's simply that the order fulfillment says payment do that for me.
if you're done I do the next thing that's orchestration.
if we're still talking about choreography versus orchestration.
you could have a stateless service some people call this a god service.
in which requests come in it decides what services in the ecosystem to call in what order.
some of them fail and succeed and then it bundles up the result.
that's not a workflow management system it is doing orchestration.
would that be an example of a non workflow management orchestration?
that could be an example of the yeah right.
I would actually love to comment out the god service.
because that's I'm discussing that a lot actually.
and that was the same human has written about that in his book.
that you have the risk of getting a god service when you use a mock situation.
and the thing what I see is that a lot of people when they say okay we do orchestration.
they think of relatively monolithic orchestration flows let's say.
so if you're doing like the order fulfillment.
and within the order fulfillment you start doing a lot of things.
which are naturally in the domain of payment.
then you start doing a lot of things in order fulfillment which you shouldn't.
and this and and that's the second part of the sentence what's mu and writes in this book.
you get the God service and basically stupid crud services.
and this is just a matter of doing good ap is for your services.
so if the payment service for example has a proper API.
it would mean the API is probably something like retrieve payment.
and then you get back either we got it or we couldn't get it and we will not get it.
so this is the API and if that's the API and you cannot make order fulfillment a god service.
because I mean the logic is in the payment service hidden behind the API.
so I think that has no direct connection to to orchestration.
but very often because then you probably have the the virtual management tool.
within the order fulfillment service.
and probably you have the capabilities of doing that very easy.
some products especially in the past with BPM and so on.
managed to move a lot of logic into these workflows and that made it a god service. and that was a bad idea actually.
we've been talking about the choreography versus orchestration.
and that orchestration doesn't necessarily require a workflow management system.
what are the characteristics of the use cases where you would want to use a workflow management system.
to do orchestration.
so the we already talked about the state handling at the diverter engine as a state machine.
so whenever it's stateful you probably want to leverage workflow engine.
and that's by the way because we're in distributed systems.
that starts to be almost everywhere.
because I mean every remote call might not be doable at that moment in time.
because the network might not be there might be broken or whatever.
or if using asynchronous communication you might have to wait for the response.
so these kind of problems start to be everywhere.
so that's the main motivation very often.
but I mean what I said earlier on there are other drivers.
so one big driver is visibility.
so whenever you do that orchestration flow in in such workflow tools.
you normally get a proper visualization.
and most of the tools or hours included.
but also most of the others use now something called ppm n.
that's an ISO standard that's where we wrote the book about.
and that's very that's a very powerful language on the one hand.
and on the other hand it's really easy to understand easy to read.
even from non-technical people even from like operations people.
which might not be developers even if they have a technical background.
so a lot of people can really understand these kind of models.
and that tries out two words I call it is DevOps.
so basically it's about business to development collaboration.
but also like a evolves like the operations part.
and that's really powerful that's very often an motivation on its own.
DPM n which stands for business process modeling notation.
that's a type of a language for defining these workflows it's not right correct?
so BPMN is for most is basically an XML file and a language definition.
so he can define like sequences doing stuff in parallel doing like splits very decide where you want to go.
but also like very mature advanced concepts like timers or timeouts you can define.
or it can also model like events.
so you can have something like like incoming events or messages.
and and decide what you want to do about it.
but also what I mentioned earlier about compensation for example these undo activities.
all of these kind of things are built into the language.
so it's very easy to express this kind of problem.
and on top of that language you always have the graphical format which is also defined.
would it be fair to say that BPMN is a domain-specific language for defining workflows?
yeah I think that's that's a good description.
yeah then a workflow becomes a type of computer program.
that the workflow management system will execute correct?
and probably one thing to note because a lot of people normally ask this.
so what what we for example do and I think most of the other engines do that as well.
so the BPMN file is an XML file so that's for me that source code.
so you can also put that into your it and into your project structure.
a version it there and the interpret is during runtime.
so we don't do any like code generation step on top of that.
so the XML file is executed directly basically.
this book you and I are discussing offline which I'll link to in the show notes.
they talked about in workflow that the process becomes a first-class entity.
which is this XML program.
if you compare that to choreography the process does not exist as a single entity.
in any one piece of code to talk about the the importance of that distinction.
yeah so I think the the main point here is I'm not sure if I go with the wording.
of being like these core entity there especially if you're into micro services.
that like the view is a bit different I see it as one artifact within one micro-service.
but anyhow I think having that model available at one place is it's powerful in many ways.
so the first is your I mean it's working code so it's one basically one point where you can look at.
how it's currently really implemented.
so normally if we see systems which are don't use orchestration.
and I see them a lot recently the first question is like okay.
how does this workflow like the business process works end-to-end.
and this normally takes a workshop of probably even days in order to figure that out.
and to really figure it out how it works.
so there's a lot of diving into code into probably the stupid tracing.
into logging into whatever it is in order to figure out how it works.
and in the orchestration approach you have like you can look at that model.
and it's it's it's running so you know it's reality and that's really powerful.
and you even get like additional information like like audit data.
and I think that's the that's so important.
because then you have also one place where it can change logic.
or we where it can discuss about changes of logic.
and what we see I mean in the past I had a lot of discussions where where people or architects said.
okay but these business processes we do they're relatively static they don't change that often.
and I'm I don't think that is so true at all occasions I see.
because we we have a lot of yeah let's say necessity for for agility in our days.
so even processes are not that stable anymore.
and then it's important to know how they are implemented at the moment in order to change anything.
what you're talking about is when you have one piece of code that executes the business process.
you know where to go to change it. correct.
you can see what it is you don't have to piece together multiple event handlers.
from multiple different services.
and if you want to make a change its straightforward more straightforward to make it exactly?
exactly and it's sometimes even so the first thing is you know the place very can't change it.
but also in terms of deploying the new version it gets much easier.
so let's assume you want to want to change these order fulfillment process for example.
and you want to do probably fetching the goods from stock before you wait for the payment.
because you want to be fast so you want to do in a parallel or whatever it is.
and if you want to make these changes you have like one service where you can go.
and there you look at the orchestration basically and you can change the flow.
and then if you use a varied flow engine these tools can also version the flow.
so if you have running order fulfillments in your system which you normally have.
then it can say ok these keep going in the old version.
and probably new instances are started in you.
versus if you compare that to the the choreographed approach.
where you have multiple services knowing what they have to do.
and whenever in certain event happens in order to make such changes.
you probably have to adjust a couple of these services redeploy them.
probably even at the same time or at least think about the timing of the deployments.
and also then keeping track of the different versions of flows that are currently going around in your system. is really really hard actually.
I want to move on now more and talk about some of the tools in depth.
you're involved in at least one one or more open source workflow management systems.
what are the projects you personally are involved with?
so I'm I have quite some history in workflow engines actually.
so personally I started I'm contributing to JBoss JVM like 12 or 13 years ago.
then I was also part of the activity team that you mentioned activity I'm earlier on.
and what we do as a company we productized and the Carmona engine.
which is basically a fork of the activity engine.
so that's where I'm involved with at most at the moment.
so that's the community PM of source platform.
and within community also do in parallel at the moment.
we started developing a new workflow engine totally from scratch.
it's called CB it's on CB dot iOS also source.
what we do there is that we really like re architect the whole engine architecture. for basically two reasons.
so whenever you want to go really in high-throughput highly scalable environments let's say.
the traditional engine architectures which are normally based on relational databases.
for persistence are not scaling enough.
and secondly also like cloud native architectures for example.
if you want to run your own queue bonitas cluster.
people are not really happy if they have to run a relational database in there.
because it's not easy to do and that's motivated us to do something like CD.
but the I'm probably I should have started with a hand phone first.
but the traditional engine architectures and that's actually true for most engines.
also come on engine there basically and the virtual engine.
and underneath there's a relational database.
where we basically just keep the state safe persistent.
let's talk some more about GB sounds like interesting architecture.
what kind of throughput can prior systems handle?
and what are you aiming for with ZB?
firstly the the numbers are always a problem so the numbers are really depending on a lot of factors.
what you do with the workflows on what kind of like like hardware or software running.
what we see at most customer scenarios is that the most of the time.
and the resources like like like memory or CPU or whatever it is.
are consumed in things that are not concern of the virtual engine.
so whatever you do around like if you call a service you probably.
if you could do a so called for example that's more expensive.
than what we do in the work flow into normally.
but to give you a number so I did like a test run like two or three years back actually on my consumer notebook.
so nothing fancy and there I could do with the current camera engine.
I could do like instances per second let's say in the hundreds.
so a couple of hundred per second that's what I could run there relatively easy.
and we have big installations really maxing that out so you can optimize that.
but think it gives you like an order-of-magnitude you can do there.
and with CB that's like we big jump there.
so if I run on the same machine if I run CB.
then I can do roughly like 30 to 40,000 instances per second.
and that's even not the end of it so we're currently still tuning it.
and the biggest but then the biggest difference is that.
see we can really scale horizontally.
so with a current engine architecture where basically even if we do cluster the engine.
we meet on the database and that means the databases the limit of the scalability.
I'm with CB where CBS an own distributed system.
and that means we and we basically store event streams on disk directly.
and do a couple of other things on disk.
and then we replicate that to followers within their own network for resilience.
and that really scares up horizontally.
and that means we have experiments where we run like millions of workflow instances per second.
so that's definitely doable and also we get the latency down to two very small numbers.
which really brings them into use cases.
where you have these low latency high throughput scenarios.
and that's basically the sweet spot where we want to go with CB at the moment.
you think of any industries or problem domains where that is.
uh where they see that type of volume?
we see that volume actually and in all industries as soon as you.
I'm shift the focus a bit so currently if we think of workflow management or business processes.
very often you think about if you go to telco for example.
you think about application processes hey I want to have a new SIM card for example.
and that's relatively rare it might be a couple of thousands per day.
or probably even like a hundred K per day if you're you're like big but that's it.
but in the same domain you have use cases if what I said earlier.
if I want to do stateful retrying for every rest call for example.
or if you wanna run a workflow to do a couple of checks every time somebody picks up the phone.
in order to make a call then this is on a complete different scaling lab.
or if you go to finance for example there's a different thing.
if you open an account or or apply for a credit card.
or if you're really in like trading and want to do that like in in real time.
and you can do the same thing for basically all the industries.
so we really shift the focus towards other use cases.
than these like relatively rare bigger business processes.
and then you you start having that scale requirement.
you're talking about older generations of these systems using a relational database.
and zeebee uses an event stream how does Evy model the state that it saves?
so how it works is basically a bit simplified probably.
but it basically works like you're having we call it records it could be an event or income.
and so when you when you why are they API for example tell CV.
please start a new workflow instance for me and that's basically a command we put that on the stream.
and then we have command or record processes internally.
and that's kind of a single writer principle.
so there's independently of how make you do the cluster there's one threat.
the whole cluster responsible for certain work for instance in order to process that command.
and then it does that it basically probably looks in the model what should happen.
and then it creates an event like work for instance created.
Oh like sequence flow like the arrow to the next step secure throat a band activity entered.
and so on so forth so we we write that as a day event Street.
and then we have multiple of these stream processors.
so one is for the core execution for example.
but we have others in order for example to write data to the audit facility for example.
so it's kind of a probably not really but comparable to what sequester.
so you can have a read model for the auditing for example for the operations.
so we have a writer doing that and so on so forth.
and what we do also like additional internally in the engine.
we keep a model or basically the current state of a workflow instance.
we keep internally in order to do particulate and how to go on.
but that's kind of an internal representation of that.
you did just mention CQRS we did a show on that and we talked about event sourcing.
where instead of storing the state you store all of the events in a particular stream.
and then you can roll those up to get the current state.
are you talking about that type of model for each instance?
we actually started with that we changed it a bit in the in the meanwhile.
so we're using its called Roxie B.
so it's it's something Facebook also uses internally in order to keep that current state.
and as soon as we process these kind of events we try to get rid of them in the runtime engine.
so we are not fully then source there so we don't keep the whole record of events.
we normally keep them but externally like in the audit facility.
so we don't need them in the core runtime the core runtime has the current state actually.
and we did that for a couple of performance reasons actually.
that makes sense.
now we're talking about applications there can be thousands of instances per second.
there could be millions of instances in flight.
events are coming in from these other collaborations.
how does CB dispatch an event to the correct instance. and ensure that that instance can handle it?
yeah so basically we have something called it called a gateway.
and the gateway knows the cluster state basically.
and there are some I actually don't want to call in all the details.
because there are some really clever things in there it's open source.
so if you fancy it you can go into all the source code.
but basically that gateway knows for example where basically to send certain messages to.
in order to correlate to the right instance.
and that's handled more or less under the hood.
there also we have a couple of algorithms how to to distribute load.
so we have I'm not sure if you're familiar with Kafka.
or the listeners are familiar with Kafka.
so we have a couple of things that are inspired also by Kafka.
so Kafka has this concept of partitions in order to scale.
so that means like for one partition and that's the same thing for us.
there's always like only one stream processor running so that doesn't really scale.
so that in our case it means there's always one threat running for one partition.
and that means we have to have multiple partitions in order to scale.
and these multiple partitions then can be distributed across different machines actually.
and then it really means that you scale out.
and there's some logic involved in order to find the right petition.
for for like creating a new workflow.
or even like sending messages to the right workflows.
but I don't want to go too much in depth in there.
and the rest is basically if you're familiar again with Kafka.
they do something or sue keeper does that what we also do like leaders and followers.
but that's for brazillian so we redistribute or we replicate the state of one broker.
to other brokers in order to not lose any data.
but in that case you always talk to the leader.
we've also been talking about retries and retry might not occur a second later.
it might occur hours later during business hours or you may wait a day.
you also might have a time limit that expires where process has to complete in a certain time.
or you give up they're a scheduler embedded in DB.
that can handle things that have to happen at a certain time. yeah definitely so short answers yes.
could you say more about that?
so not really much at the moment so we're currently with CB Verena in a let's say rd state.
so we're currently targeting production ready release end of the year but we're not yet.
and we're currently and building a couple of these concepts they're on the schedule.
so that might change until we have that recording from today online.
so I don't want to go into too much detail in there. okay oh yeah it's a different question.
could you talk generally about the responsibilities in the design of a scheduler.
within a workflow management system.
drawing upon your experience in that domain.
so scheduling I mean it's an important part of these kind of workflow engine.
so there there are different aspects of that.
so normally there are moments when the virtual engine has to get active on its own.
which is the most prominent use case being timer.
so you say okay there's a certain time out.
or you are in some processes you want to wait for a certain time until you move on.
and that means there must be some kind of schedule Allah.
who basically picks up the instances at the right moment at time.
and this has to be done like you know in a large scale.
it still has to be a in a very performant way.
and for example in the current Carmona engine.
we invested a lot of effort in in prioritizing certain things.
so I'm that you for example make sure.
if you have like low latency requirements for certain workflows.
that there are process before others.
like if you have like an like an application workflow.
which ones for a couple of days and normally delaying that by a few minutes doesn't matter much.
whereas if you have like an almost real-time requirement it matters a lot.
so there are a couple of things to do right there these kind of scheduling.
so it's not totally easy.
could you address the issue of me I'll call this transactionality.
in that we want at the end of the process all the steps to have been done.
and we probably want most of these steps to be done once.
we don't want to pay twice ship the product twice.
but you can be dealing with external systems.
or you're generally not in an environment where you can get a database transaction.
how does the workflow management ensure that things are done the correct number of times.
so I would differentiate that to tool stacks we currently have.
if I look at your engines like the kimono and B pen product.
that's basically it's a written in Java and you can integrate that within your java transaction management.
if you like so there we have quite a number of customers actually.
who basically leverage real asset transaction.
which combined the the virtual engine and some business logic on the database. it only works if you're in the same database.
I mean otherwise you get x8 transactions then and this normally it doesn't really work.
so it's possible but I wouldn't wouldn't take it as a default case in all other cases.
and that's for CVE or if we do remote calls rests or soap or your PC or whatever it is.
then you don't have these asset transactions and in this case I mean.
I and most of my talks currently I have really a lot of slides on idempotency.
because I think idempotency is one of the most important concepts every developer should be aware of.
so idempotency means that I can call a service twice and that's not a problem.
so it either doesn't matter or the service can detect that this is a duplicate and just ignores it.
we could call and in these kind of architectures basically in every distributed system.
you should do services that are idempotent that's really hard.
if you don't have item of services.
and that means if you if you leverage the workflow engine for example.
in order to call other services you normally do it in a way.
that you say okay if I if I can't commit my local transaction for example.
then I might retry that thing I might call it twice.
that's hard to avoid because and there can make a couple of drawings.
and basically prove that it's you can always have moments.
where you have no idea if you call the other service or not.
so there is not a really good way around of retrying.
so that's what also happens in there and that's what you should plan for.
on the other side of the equation like if some service calls the virtual engine for example.
and CB we have and also in Kiruna Bambi have prepared it in a way.
that you can have idempotent start for example for workflow instance.
so whenever you call that and you call it twice it doesn't matter.
so we recognize we already started at work for instance so we are idempotent as well.
and i think if you do that right then things starts to play out relatively nicely.
the other thing about consistency there is what I mentioned earlier.
like if you have a couple of things like two or three steps in a sequence third fails.
you cannot roll back then you use these undo functionality like built-in the main language.
you talk a bit more about the undo functionality and give an example of when that would.
I normally use the let's say the classical example.
so whenever you're looking like if you if you search on Google for saga pattern.
you always find the same example so I also want to use that today which is a trip walking.
so you want to book a trip and then the first thing you might wanna book is the like the hotel.
then a rental car and then a flight.
and then it might be that the flight cannot be for whatever reason you get an error there.
but you already booked a hotel in the car.
and that means you have to make sure you cancel the car and the hotel.
and if you do that in BPMN in these virtual models.
it means that for every activity like the hotel.
you can define directly the activity which does the undo like cancel the hotel for example.
and then the virtual engine keeps track of which activities were executed already.
and make sure they are compensated correctly and that's done under the hood.
and and stateful and reliable and that's basically this kind of undo functionality is there.
I don't know if I would do it in this order but suppose I did the car first the hotel and flights.
which are the most variable I'm not able to book the flight now.
I need to undo a car in the hotel because I don't need them anymore.
and that's that's the responsibility of the undo phase correct? correct.
and that's again by the way you could do the same thing and with choreography.
oh so I also had that example with choreography.
but there you also see that it's really hard to keep track how the other undo face is doing.
and if you do it with BPM - obviously orchestration.
so you have like one word flow model where exactly the.
okay this is the first these are the steps and these are the undo things you have to do.
one thing which is also interesting and to look at.
so the saga patterns you already mentioned that.
so normally you're also order the activities by let's say by risk or by costs.
so it's not a surprise that I do the hotel first because it's normally cheap to cancel. or or for free to cancel.
I would have thought I would do the flight first.
because that's the most risky thing and you wanna get that out of the way.
because I don't need the hotel or the car if I can't get the flight.
am I thinking about this the wrong way? I think in this example I would do it the other way around.
because if for whatever reason you cannot do the car or the hotel.
like canceling the flight is really expensive.
yeah and the other way around it's normally relatively cheap.
but there are other situations where where this kind of thinking is pretty much valid.
so the important thing is that it matters if it order you do that.
which for example for asset transaction if you really can roll back it doesn't.
but in this case it does because you have like intermediary states which are really committed.
so you really have to think about the order I think that's the message.
okay I'm gonna change the subject a bit now talking about monitoring and observability.
you did touch on this a little while ago.
and we also talked about having a process defined as a piece of code.
or a first-class entity where now it may be easier to observe or visualize the process.
what kind of opportunities for visual understanding do these workflow engines give?
and you could pick one of them that you work on or speak in general.
so I always can comment best on the tools I know which are basically the tools we do.
so there are multiple ways first of all to define this kind of workflow.
so for us we can either do that in code so you could define a workflow in Java code for example.
there we also have kind of a yes l-like a few and programming thing.
and then we generate the XML and the graphical visualization out of that. or you start with the visual.
I normally when I discussed with people which are new to workflow management.
I very often if they are developers I very often start with the Java DSL actually.
because it shows that there is no hidden complexity no magic in these kind of graphical models.
because a lot of developer are often afraid of practical models.
which i think is because of a lot of things which were going around with MBA and so on.
but whenever it starts to be more complex people are naturally using the graphical modeler.
it's much easier to understand to do.
and then you have this model independently of if you did it in code or graphics.
but having the graphical model for all the later on phases.
like looking into it when you're running the stuff or in operations for example.
then you exactly see okay I have a problem at this point.
and this is how I did get there.
you see exactly which steps were executed at what time what's the the data attached.
and so on and so forth so you see a lot of lot of context information for that.
so that I think is really valuable there.
and also like the audit data like we have to a cult optimizer.
can load like push all the data from probably in different engines in there.
and then it can make a lot of analyzes on that like I'm heat maps they are very very popular.
so you can see like what are the most frequent hearthis.
or you can make like duration heat map so where it's typically really slow.
or we can define SLA s and see where it's slower than the SLA.
and these kind of things so there's a lot of things you can do with it.
yeah for example we also have like a small community extension.
which was actually I'm contributed by a couple of people from the community where.
and we also leverage the BPM and model for test coverage.
so you see for every test case like a J unit test case for example you right.
you see the exact path which was taken.
so if their test case fails for whatever reason you can direct it for example in Jenkins.
like jump to the visual and see okay it's executed till that step.
and that's where the test case crashed and that makes it very often easier to understand what's going on.
because very often that happens like a year after you wrote the initial code or so.
so if I could summarize here until you're talking about the definition phase.
where you are creating the workflow and then moving on to operations where it's running.
and you could use the same visual representation.
but you could be looking at how much activity is going on in each phase of your workflow.
and then Aude it which you mentioned a couple of times I maybe we could come back to.
so by audit data you mean that the system generates some kind of either log or structured records.
describing what it's been doing.
and then you can take that and do further analytics or monitoring on top of that.
correct. so we also call that history data.
so basically what the engine rides is which steps were executed at what time.
and what workflow instances were executed and so on and so forth.
and this can be either used for like really looking into the history of one instance.
either because it's 40 or probably in for compliance reasons.
so you want to want to know why this work for instance ended up in the whatever rejected face.
or something like that but you can also do a lot of like really analyzes and on top of that.
to understand if the verb flow is really yeah behaving in the way it should.
or if it's optimal or there's like potential to improve that.
I could see that being very useful in the case you're talking about.
on an individual case what went wrong with this order why didn't we ship it.
but also in a statistical sense learning about we as a company.
how good a job are we doing at fulfilling orders.
what percentage of the time do we have to retry the charge.
and all these other ways you can understand the performance of your business.
in carrying out its objectives correct?
and we we also have like a lot of fun stories we see like in a couple of product.
it happens that after a virtual went to production after a while.
we looked at this kind of data.
and we saw that certain paths which were really really important during implementation.
because that's an exceptional case we have to cover.
and there were a lot of effort in development going into this special.
and was never executed that happens really off.
and then these tools give you a proof look.
this was never executed in the last in the past six month.
do we really have to maintain that code can we throw it away.
and that this is real evidence I mean that's data you can use in order to make an argument.
what question like to wrap up with here.
if we and I T we'd like to adopt a new programming language or a new type of app server.
the business side may not care as long as the SLA zermatt.
when you're changing from either ad hoc or choreography.
to adopting workflow management system.
is that something that business is inherently involved in that process?
so we have different approaches for different customers.
so the good thing is that but these business processes and for especially BPMN.
and the visibility is that you can always involve business.
because they they start understanding the visuals.
and they are normally really impressed by this kind of data they get and heat maps they get.
and so for example if your choreography.
what we sometimes do as a first step is just to attach like the virtual engine.
and then have kind of a tracking process it doesn't control anything.
it doesn't do anything like actively.
but it it correlates all the events on a bus for example.
and then you start seeing this kind of instances. and you start collecting this kind of data.
and probably even attach like a first SLA like a timeout.
if we don't end up to this point within a certain time frame we should do something.
and that's always easy to involve business with these kind of things.
and I think that's a big opportunity also to get business and IT closer together.
they're great I said that was gonna be my last question.
but that does make me think about.
you have talked about these timers you can have a condition.
where we've charged the customer we agree to ship product within one day after charging.
and now it's gone to the second day we haven't shipped within these processes.
with this via like a business level exception.
or how does this type of case.
where we we're not doing the process correctly from a business standpoint.
to uphold obligations to the the customer how does that fit into the the modeling.
or the execution and who gets to somebody get paged or what happens.
when we've when these cases occur?
so there are two levels for it to do so the first is like let's say the technical level.
so that's more like the paging level or what we do for example optimize.
very can be fine SL A's on certain things.
and then you say okay this task must be executed within a certain time frame for example.
and if this doesn't happen then this is kind of a violation of the SLA.
and this would be more or less something which probably triggers a pager.
the second level is you can really make it part of the business workflow.
and the business process so let's say you have that order fulfillment process.
and then BPMN as the language supports that is say.
okay there's a certain phase for example within that.
and if that takes longer in a certain timeframe then I want to do something.
in this case you really model what you want to do.
it could be that you whatever put that in the human task management.
that somebody looks at it.
or it could be that you're apologized to the to the customer.
or it could be that you cancel the order because it took too long.
and that's I mean that's a business decision so and that really it belongs there.
great of that pretty much comes to the end of our time burned.
is there anything else you wanted to add that we haven't covered?
I think there's a lot we haven't covered but I think that was a hopefully good overview.
so I'm fine with what we spoke about today.
and I think there's a lot of material like in the blog posts and in other talks online.
if I got people interested in that they probably want to read it up there.
where it's the best place for people to go to find your work?
so they the easiest would be probably I have an A homepage it's been wicked or I.
oh you probably have it in the notes and there are a link at least all my talks and my block is linked.
and that's probably a good starting point if you don't find your way through another.
but also to send me an email to ping me on Twitter or whatever works for you.
and then we can probably also discuss or I can send you a couple of things linked to everything.
animal links is the open-source project burned it's been a pleasure speaking to you.
thank you for appearing on software engineering radio.
thank you for software engineering radio.
this has been Robert blumen thank you for listening.
thanks for listening to Nessie radio.
an educational program brought to you by Triple E software magazine.
for more about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at SE - radio net.
to provide feedback you can comment on each episode on the website.
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter.
or through our slack channel at SC radio.com.
you can also email us at team @ SC - radio net.
this and all other episodes of se radio is licensed under Creative Commons license 2.5. thanks for listening.